[Music]
sorgum is the Forgotten grain the United
States is actually the number one
producer of sorghum but it's typically
not used to produce food for American
consumers instead it's produced mainly
for feeding livestock or as pet food or
even building materials but it's
actually eaten as is stable in other
parts of the world such as Asia and
Africa uh where it's been eaten for
thousands of years making it currently
the fifth most popular grain grown after
wheat corn rice and barley beating out
oats and Rye because sorghum is
glutenfree because it can be
definitively considered safe for people
with celiac disease we're starting to
see it emerge as actual human food in
the US so I decided to look into just
how healthy it might be uh protein Wise
It's comparable to other grains but
since when do we have to worry about
getting enough protein fiber is what
Americans are desperately deficient in
and sorum does pull towards the front of
the pack the micronutrient composition
is relatively unremarkable here's how it
rates on minerals for example where
sorghum shines is on polyphenol content
polyphenols are plant compounds
associated with reduced risk of a number
of chronic diseases including cancer
cardiovascular diseases neuro degenerate
disorders and even all cause mortality
and if you compare different grains
sorghum really does pull ahead helping
to explain why its antioxidant power is
so much higher now sorghum gets its
grainy little butt kicked when it comes
to fruits and vegetables but in terms of
compared to other grains sorghum based
breakfast cereal for example might have
like eight times the antioxidant than a
whole wheat based cereal but I mean what
we care about is not anti antioxidant
activity in in test tube but antioxidant
activity within our body if you measure
the antioxidant capacity of your blood
after eating regular pasta it goes up a
little if you replace 30% of the wheat
flour with sorghum flour it doesn't go
up much more but if you eat 30% red
sorghum flour pasta the antioxidant
capacity in your bloodstream shoots up
like 15 fold I see there multiple types
of sorghum there's black sorghum white
sorghum and red sorghum this is how they
look in Grain form there's evidently a
yellow sorghum too and red sorghum and
especially black have like you know
legit you know fruit and vegetable level
antioxidant activity the problem is I
can't find any of the colored ones I
mean I can go online and buy you know
red or black rice purple blue or red
popping corn and you know purple or
black barley but I I can't find red or
black sorghum hopefully someday uh but
uh but you can find white sorghum for
about four bucks a pound I mean does it
have any unique Health promoting
attributes uh it's promoted as an
underutilized serial whole grain with
the potential to assist in the
prevention of chronic disease uh but
what is the effect of soron consumption
on health outcomes an epidemiological
study in China found lower esophageal
cancer mortality rates in areas that ate
more Millet and sorghum compared to you
know corn and wheat but that may have
been more due to avoiding a
contaminating fungus then from the
benefit in the Sorghum itself I mean
though it's possible I mean just as oats
are the only source of you know
avenanthramides which give oats some
unique health benefits sorghum even
white sorghum contain unique pigments
known as three deoxy enth thein which
are strong inducers of some of the
detoxifying enzymes in our liver and can
inhibit the growth of human cancer cells
growing in a Petri dish compared to you
know red cabbage which has just regular
anthes and pigment
uh but note that white sorum didn't do
much worse than red or black which have
way more of the unique 3D oxy anthes and
so maybe it's just a general sorghum
effect I mean you don't know until you
put it to the test sorum was found to
suppress tumor growth and metastasis in
human breast cancer
xenographs what does that mean the
research conclude that sorghum could be
used as an inexpensive natural cancer
therapy without any side effects
strongly recommending the use of sorghum
as an edible therapeutic agent
possessing tumor suppression and anti-
metastatic effects on human breast
cancer but xenograph means human breast
cancer implanted in a
mouse yes the human tumors grew slower
in the mice fed sorghum extracts and
blocked metastasis to the lung and did
the same for human colon cancer that
again was in mice which can't
necessarily be translated to how human
cancers would grow in humans since for
example not only do these mice not have
a human immune system they hardly have
any immune system and they're bred
without a thymus gland which is where
cancer fighting immunity largely
originates I mean how else could you
keep the mouse's immune system from
ejecting the human tissue outright right
but this immunosuppression makes these
kind of mouse models that much more
artificial and that much more
difficult to extrapolate to humans and
that's a lot of what we see in the
sorgum literature in vitro data like in
test tubes and Petri dishes and rats and
mice there had just been this critical
missing piece of the puzzle needed to
link laboratory data to actual benefits
in humans missing that is
until now thankfully we now have human
Interventional studies which we'll
explore
next